{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This leader’s cause was damaged by constant feuds with Li Zongren over control of the army. This man was forced to form the Second United Front with his enemies after he was kidnapped in the Xi’an [shee-ahn] incident. This man’s wife, Soong Mei-Ling, tried to promote the “four virtues” during the New Life Movement. For ten points, name this successor of Sun Yat-sen, a Kuomintang leader who set up his base in Taiwan after losing the Chinese Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Chiang Kai-Shek",
        "Jiang Jieshi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Authors like William Simms and Caroline Hentz wrote works in a genre named for their opposition to this novel. The title character of this novel was inspired by Josiah Henson, who wrote two autobiographies detailinghislifeafterhefledtoCanada.Manysouthernersrebuttedthisnovelbyclaimingitmisrepresented friendly relationships between masters and slaves. For ten points, name this 1852 novel by Harriet Beecher Stowe.",
      "answer": [
        "Uncle Tom’s Cabin,",
        "Life Among the Lowly"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Croatian War began at one of these locations called Maksimir following a fight between a police officer and Zvonimir Boban. One of these places in Croke became the site of an infamous massacre perpetrated by British troops on Bloody Sunday. The Sun newspaper was effectively banned from one city after it erroneously claimed that the Hillsborough disaster at one of these facilities was caused by onrushing Liverpool fans. For ten points, name these places where teams like Arsenal and Manchester United play football.",
      "answer": "soccer stadiums"
    },
    {
      "question": "The command to conduct this event was allegedly caught on audio tape by Terry Strubbe. This event, which may have been caused by people throwing rocks at a patrolman’s Jeep, was witnessed by John Filo, who took a photograph of Mary Ann Vecchio kneeling next to Jeffrey Miller’s body. The President’s Commission on Campus Unrest was created in the wake of, for ten points, what tragedy in which the Ohio National Guard opened fire on Vietnam War protesters?",
      "answer": "Kent State shootings"
    },
    {
      "question": "At one battle, this ruler urged his men never to “lose sight of my panache” and noted that they were “on the road to honor and victory.” This man, who defeated the Duke of Mayenne at Ivry, was killed by Fran¸cois Ravaillac. The Guise faction in the French Wars of Religion was opposed by this king, who protected Protestant rights by proclaiming the Edict of Nantes. For ten points, name this first Bourbon king of France who was a Huguenot before he converted to Catholicism, declaring “Paris is well worth a mass.”",
      "answer": [
        "Henry IV of France",
        "Henry III of Navarre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A thinker from this country wrote Dialectical and Historical Materialism, which laid the groundwork for this country’s political ideology. In the book Our Revolution, another thinker from this country argued against another thinker from here with the idea of a “permanent revolution.” One early leader of this country outlined his political philosophy in the “April Theses.” For ten points, name this former country, whose political thinkers included Leon Trotsky, Joseph Stalin, and Vladmir Lenin. ANSWER:SovietUnion(orUSSR;orUnionofSovietSocialistRepublics;acceptCCCPorSoyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik;promptonRussia;promptonGeorgia;promptonUkraine) (7) In a publicity stunt, Andrew Carnegie led an elephant across this city’s Eads Bridge to prove the stability of the steel used in its construction. This city’s Forest Park hosted the 1904 World’s Fair. A national park in this city, which was formerly called the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, contains a massive steel catenary designed by Eero Saarinen. The Gateway Arch is in, for ten points, what large city in eastern Missouri?",
      "answer": "St. Louis"
    },
    {
      "question": "A commander in this battle claimed that out of control Ho-Chunk allies started the attack. Despite being shot in the head and both thighs in this battle, Spier Spencer continued to command his Yellow Jackets. The victorious general in this battle succeeded in destroying Prophetstown and, twenty-nine years later, used his fame from this battle to win the Election of 1840. Shawnee forces were defeated in Indiana in, for ten points, what 1811 battle that gave William Henry Harrison a nickname used in his campaign with “Tyler, too”?",
      "answer": "Battle of Tippecanoe"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events divided its participants into “new” and “old” lights based on their fervor. Another of these events led Charles Finney to describe western New York as the “burned over district.” Samuel Davies was a leader of one of these events, during which humanity was compared to a spider hanging over a fire in the “Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God” sermon of Jonathan Edwards. For ten points, name these periods of American Christian religious revival.",
      "answer": "First and/or Second Great Awakenings"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed that he drew from the general theory of relativity to create a new religion called Universalism. This man came to power after a foreign power invaded in Operation Weserubu¨ng, which enabled him to succeed Johan Nygaardsvold after King Haakon VII fled the country. In 1945, this founder of the Nasjonal Samling party was executed outside Akershus fortress for his collaboration with the Nazis. For ten points, name this treasonous president of Norway.",
      "answer": "Vidkun Quisling"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An inscription found at Jarrow claims that this structure’s namesake built it due to “divine instruction.” The Stanegate was a road that followed a similar path to this structure, which contains a ditch once named after Agricola. Along the North Sea, this structure terminates at Solway Firth. This 73 mile long structure was intended to keep the Picts and other Celtic groups out of Roman territory. A cousin of Trajan names, for ten points, what wall in northern England?",
        "answer": [
          "Hadrian’s Wall",
          "Vallum Aelium"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Antonine Wall was built 100 miles north of Hadrian’s Wall, but it was abandoned by this last of the Five Good Emperors in 164 AD.",
        "answer": "Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Bancroft’s recommendation of this man was unanimously accepted, ending a debate between Lewis Cass and Martin Van Buren. This president’s administration was able to work with Richard Pakenham to resolve a border dispute, despite this man’s support of the slogan “54-40 or fight.” This president gained Southern support by replacing the infamous “Black” Tariff with the Walker Tariff. For ten points, name this 11th president, a believer in manifest destiny who oversaw the Mexican-American War.",
        "answer": "James Knox Polk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "British Ambassador Richard Pakenham eventually agreed with the US on a resolution to this dispute, the subject of the “54-40 or fight” slogan. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": [
          "Oregon boundary dispute",
          "descriptions regarding the border between the Oregon territory and British territory in Canada"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This initiative was brought into effect by the Berlin Decree and subsequently escalated by the Orders in Council, which prompted Scandinavian nations to form the Second League of Armed Neutrality. Following the Battle of Friedland and the signing of the Treaty of Tilsit, one nation joined this initiative; however, that nation later deserted this system, prompting a French invasion of Russia. For ten points, name this Napoleonic system that attempted to impose an economic blockade on Great Britain.",
        "answer": "Continental System"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Portugal’s refusal to join the Continental System ultimately led to this war in 1808. It included the Battle of Salamanca.",
        "answer": "Peninsular War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Rather than using traditional hymns, Michael Tippett incorporated five of these pieces into his oratorio written in response to Kristallnacht, A Child of Our Time. Williams Arms Fisher published an arrangement of seventy of these songs and adapted the Largo second movement of Dvorak’s ninth symphony into one of these works. The Fisk Jubilee Singers famously recorded many of these works, including “Swing Low, Sweet Chariot.” Instruments like early banjos sometimes accompanied the singers of, for ten points, what kind of religious songs, many of which were written by slaves in the American south?",
        "answer": [
          "African-American spirituals",
          "additional information",
          "sorrow songs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This black sociologist described spirituals as “sorrow songs” in his 1903 essay collection The Souls of Black Folk, which opens each chapter with a selection of spiritual music.",
        "answer": "William Edward Burghardt W.E.B. Du Bois"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A decade of turmoil in this country was ushered in with the July Apostasy by king Constantine II. After several weak civilian governments, the Regime of the Colonels took over and ruled this country from 1967 to 1974; when civilian rule was restored, PASOK and New Democracy dominated this country’s politics until the rise of Syriza in the wake of the debt crisis of the early 2010s. For ten points, name this country where Alexis Tsipras was replaced as Prime Minister in 2019.",
        "answer": "Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The rule of the colonels was ended by the failure of enosis, a Greek word meaning “union” that described the goal of uniting Greece with what other country?",
        "answer": "Cyprus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Earl van Dorn’s defeat in this state while trying to retake the railroad junction at Corinth was a major loss for the South. Another Union victory in this state, where John C. Pemberton surrendered to the Union, cut off Texas and Arkansas from the rest of the Confederacy. Ulysses Grant led a successful siege of Vicksburg, a fortress town on this state’s namesake river. For ten points, name this Confederate state where, in 1863, Union forces seized the capital of Jackson.",
        "answer": "Mississippi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Confederates surrendered Vicksburg on this day in 1863, one day after the last day of Gettysburg.",
        "answer": "July 4th"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire’s founder influenced the Battle of Ipsus by granting 300 war elephants to Seleucus. Another ruler of this empire was named for the drop of poison atop his head and was advised by Kautilya, author of the Arthashastra. The most famous ruler of this empire fought a war whose carnage prompted him to issue a series of remorseful rock edicts and convert to Buddhism. For ten points, name this ancient Indian empire once ruled by Ashoka.",
        "answer": "Mauryan Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ashoka converted to Buddhism after witnessing the devastation of this war in eastern India.",
        "answer": "Kalinga War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man translated the Pastoral Care to help local bishops train priests; that work is the oldest known English book. This man, who had his life chronicled by Asser, promulgated his law code within the “Doom Book.” This man’s victories at Edington and Chippenham against Guthrum pacified the Viking threat. The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle was published during the reign of, for ten points, what “great” king from Wessex?",
        "answer": "Alfred the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pastoral Care, the oldest known book in English, is a translation of a work by this “great” pope, who sent a mission to England in 596. His reforms to church liturgy included a larger use of plainchant.",
        "answer": [
          "Gregory I",
          "Saint Gregory the Great",
          "Gregorian chant"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Jamestown",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Colony and future state of which it was the capital.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "City, originally called the Middle Plantation, that replaced it as capital in 1699.",
          "answer": "Williamsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cash crop, cultivated by John Rolfe, that helped save the colony.",
          "answer": "tobacco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer and governor who told the first settlers “he that will not work, shall not eat.”",
          "answer": "John Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "1676 rebellion against William Berkeley in which Jamestown was burned.",
          "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name given to the harsh winter of 1609 that resulted in the death of 90% of Jamestown’s population.",
          "answer": "Starving Time"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby native confederacy that clashed with Jamestown; Pocahontas was a member of these people.",
          "answer": "Powhatan Confederacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "English naval officer who kidnapped Pocahontas and later used Jamestown as his base of operations for raids against Acadia.",
          "answer": "Samuel Argall"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Italian Unification",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Century in which the Risorgimento was conducted.",
          "answer": [
            "19th century",
            "1800s"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City that became the capital of unified Italy.",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by Pius IX [ninth], who opposed the efforts.",
          "answer": [
            "Pope",
            "Bishop of Rome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom, based on an island off the Italian coast, where Francis II was deposed in the Expedition of the Thousand.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Sicily",
            "Kingdom of the Two Sicilies"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "General who led the Expedition of the Thousand and whose followers wore red shirts.",
          "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi"
        },
        {
          "question": "First king of unified Italy, who maintained the regnal number “the Second” despite leading a new country.",
          "answer": "Victor Emmanuel II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom ruled by that man prior to unification, explaining why he kept “the Second” in his title.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia"
        },
        {
          "question": "River where the redshirts of the Matese Legion prevented Francis II’s troops from reaching Naples.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Volturno",
            "Volturnus"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Latin American Leaders",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Alberto Fujimori was imprisoned in Lima after fleeing Japan.",
          "answer": "Peru"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the PRI’s Enrique Pen˜a Nieto was succeeded by Andr´es Manuel L´opez Obrador in 2018.",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Dilma Rousseff was impeached in 2016.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Manuel Noriega was besieged by rock music in the Vatican embassy.",
          "answer": "Panama"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Venezuela who called George W. Bush “the devil” at the UN in 2006.",
          "answer": "Hugo Chavez"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruler who became President of Haiti after the death of his similarly brutal father in 1971.",
          "answer": [
            "Jean-Claude Duvalier",
            "Baby Doc"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2016 Nobel Prize winner for negotiating a peace referendum with FARC.",
          "answer": "Juan Manuel Santos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorado leader who earned the nickname “Colonel Trunk” after being smuggled to safety in the back of a car in 1948.",
          "answer": "Alfredo Stroessner"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Three members of this family received the Legion of Honor in 1909, including Katharine, who worked as a publicist during their tour of Europe. This family produced the Van Cleve catalog from their home base in Dayton, Ohio, where they operated a (20 pts)",
        "bicycle shop. Two members of this family added a three-axis control system to a (10 pts)",
        "“Flyer” that they tested near Kitty Hawk, North Carolina. For ten points, name this family of engineers that included siblings Katharine, Wilbur, and Orville."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wright family",
        "Katharine, Wilbur, and/or Orville Wright"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Treaty of San Stefano gave this ruler Bessarabia while guaranteeing Bulgarian independence. A carriage containing Napoleon III and this ruler was targeted by an assassin at the 1867 World’s Fair. (20 pts)",
        "Nikolay Milyutin helped this ruler liberalize by creating the Zemstvo local government system, and this man’s foreign minister Prince Gorchakov sold (10 pts)",
        "Alaska to the US. In 1881, this man was assassinated in St. Petersburg by the People’s Will terrorist group. For ten points, name this Russian ruler who emancipated the serfs in 1861."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alexander II",
        "Alexander Nikolayevich Romanov"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure advises a king who goes mad and lives in the wilderness until his “hair grew like feathers” in a book that describes the rise of Darius the Mede, an otherwise unattested king who ruled before (20 pts)",
        "Cyrus the Great. As an adviser to the Babylonian king Belshazzar, this figure interprets mysterious writing that (10 pts)",
        "appears on a wall. This figure’s namesake book contains the story of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. For ten points, name this Biblical adviser of Nebuchadnezzar who miraculously survived being thrown into the lion’s den."
      ],
      "answer": "Daniel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A self-portrait from this movement shows Tamara de Lempicka in a Green Bugatti with half-lidded eyes and a tight hat. This movement’s three-dimensional varieties included Zigzag and Streamline Moderne, which emphasized long, smooth horizontal curves on (20 pts)",
        "cars and numerous buildings built by the Works Progress Administration. A poster from this movement shows three golden towers of the Federal Building at the Chicago (10 pts)",
        "World’s Fair in 1933. For ten points, name this opulent, early-twentieth-century art movement that focused on bold, geometric designs, characterized by the Chrysler Building."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Art Deco",
        "Style Moderne",
        "Zigzag",
        "Streamline Moderne",
        "Moderne until mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was the site of Operation Dragon Rouge, where foreign special forces had to be deployed to rescue hostages during the Simba Uprising. A crisis in this country was almost mediated by UN Secretary-General Dag (20 pts)",
        "Hammarskjold [“hammer”-sk’yold], who died in a plane crash in Northern Rhodesia en route to a peace conference. The (10 pts)",
        "Katanga Crisis took place in this country, where Joseph Kasa-Vubu was replaced by a man who briefly renamed this country Zaire. For ten points, name this African country where Mobutu Sese Seko led from Kinshasa."
      ],
      "answer": "Democratic Republic of the Congo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech attacks a governor whose “lips [drip] with the words of interposition and nullification.” The writer of this speech claims to have received a check from America that was marked (20 pts)",
        "“insufficient funds” but goes on to describe former slaves and slaveowners sitting together at the “table of brotherhood.” The hope that future generations “will not be (10 pts)",
        "judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character” is proclaimed in, for ten points, what speech given at the 1963 March on Washington by Martin Luther King, Jr.?"
      ],
      "answer": "I Have a Dream speech"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, student Benno Ohnesorg was killed during a protest against the Shah of Iran. This country was the subject of a declaration by French foreign minister Robert Schuman that paved the way for the European (20 pts)",
        "Coal and Steel Community. An economic miracle in this country began under Konrad Adenauer, and it adopted the policy of (10 pts)",
        "“ostpolitik” under Willy Brandt to ease tensions with its neighbor. For ten points, name this former country with capital Bonn that was re-unified with its eastern neighbor in 1990."
      ],
      "answer": "West Germany"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To deal with members of this group after the 1838 Battle of Crooked River, Lilburn Boggs put out Missouri Executive Order 44, an “Extermination Order.” A leader of this group who was killed in Carthage, Illinois allegedly met with (20 pts)",
        "Moroni, an angel who handed down golden plates that became this religion’s central text. Members of this religion briefly created the state of (10 pts)",
        "Deseret, which was governed by Brigham Young. Joseph Smith founded, for ten points, what Christian denomination that is the majority religion of Utah?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mormons"
    }
  ]
}